SCHWEIK’S MISADVENTURES ON THE TRAIN 

There were <cg>three passengers</cg> in a <p1>second-class compartment of the Prague-Budejovice express</p1>.
<c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1>, opposite whom <c2>an elderly and entirely bald  gentleman</c2> was sitting, and <c3>Schweik</c3>, who was standing  modestly <p2>in the corridor</p2> and was just preparing to listen  to a fresh storm of abuse from <c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1> who,  regardless of the presence of the <c2>bald-headed civilian</c2>, 
kept yelling at <c3>Schweik</c3> throughout the journey, that <c3>he</c3> was a God-forsaken idiot and similar things.
The cause of the trouble was a trifling matter, a slight discrepancy in the number of pieces of luggage that <c3>Schweik</c3> was looking after. “One of our trunks has been stolen, <c3>you</c3> say,” snarled  the <c1>lieutenant</c1> at <c3>Schweik</c3>. “That’s a fine thing to tell anyone, <c3>you</c3> <c3>jackass</c3>. What was in that trunk?” 
“Nothing at all, <c1>sir</c1>,” replied <c3>Schweik</c3>, with <c3>his</c3> eyes  glued to the bald head of the <c2>civilian</c2>, who was sitting opposite to the <c1>lieutenant</c1>, and <c2>who</c2> appeared to be taking no interest whatever in the matter, but was reading the Neue Freie Presse. “All that was in that trunk was a looking-glass from <px>the bedroom</px> and an iron clothes hanger from <px>the passage</px>, so that <cg>we</cg> didn’t really lose 
anything, because the looking-glass and the hanger belonged to the <c4>landlord</c4>.” 
“Shut up, <c3>Schweik</c3>,” the <c1>lieutenant</c1> shouted. “<c1>I</c1>’ll  deal with <c3>you</c3> when we get to <p2>Budejovice</p2>. Do <c3>you</c3> know  I’m going to have <c3>you</c3> locked up?” 
“Beg to report, <c1>sir</c1>, I don’t,” said <c3>Schweik</c3> blandly. “<c1>You</c1> never mentioned anything to <c3>me</c3> about it before, <c1>sir</c1>.” 
The <c1>leutenant</c1> gritted <c1>his</c1> teeth, sighed, took a copy of the Bohemia from <c1>his</c1> pocket and began to read news about great victories, and the exploits of the German sub-marine “E” in the Mediterranean. Just when <c1>he</c1> had come to a report about a new German invention for blowing cities up by means of special triple detonating bombs dropped from aeroplanes, <c1>he</c1> was interrupted by  the voice of <c3>Schweik</c3>, who was addressing the <c2>bald-headed gentleman</c2> :
“Excuse me, <c2>guv’nor</c2>, but ain’t <c2>you</c2> <c5>Mr. Purkrdbek</c5>, <c5>agent of the Slavia Bank</c5>?” 
When the <c2>bald-headed gentleman</c2> made no reply, <c3>Schweik</c3> said to the <c1>lieutenant</c1>: “Beg to report, <c1>sir</c1>, I <t1>once</t1> read in the paper that the average man has 60,000 to 70,000 hairs on his head and that many examples show black hair is thinner as a rule.” 
And <c3>he</c3> continued remorselessly: 
“Then there was <cx>a doctor</cx> who said that loss of hair was due to mental disturbance during confinements.” 
But now a dreadful thing happened. The <c2>bald-headed gentleman</c2> jumped towards <c3>Schweik</c3> and shouted : 
“Get out of here, <c3>you</c3> <c3>dirty swine</c3>,” and having hustled <c3>him</c3> into <p3>the corridor</p3>, returned to the carnage, where <c2>he</c2> gave <c1>the lieutenant</c1> a little surprise by introducing <c2>himself</c2>. 
Evidently there had been a mistake. The <c2>bald-headed man</c2> was not <c5>Mr. Purkrdbek</c5>, <c5>agent of the Slavia Bank</c5>, but merely <c2>Major-General von Schwarzburg</c2>. The <c2>major-general</c2> was just proceeding in mufti on a series of garrison inspections and was <t2>now</t2> about to pay a surprise visit to <p2>Budejovice</p2>. 
<c2>He</c2> was the most fearsome major-general who had ever walked the earth, and if <c2>he</c2> found anything amiss, the 
following dialogue would ensue between <c2>him</c2> and the <c6>garrison commandant</c6> : 
“Have <c6>you</c6> got a revolver?” 
“Yes, <c2>sir</c2>.” 
“All right, then. If <c2>I</c2> were in <c6>your</c6> place, <c2>I</c2>’d know what to do with it. This isn’t a garrison, it’s a pigsty.” 
And, as a matter of fact, there were always a certain 
number who shot themselves after one of <c2>his</c2> inspections, 
whereupon <c2>Major-General von Schwarzburg</c2> would always observe with satisfaction : 
“That’s the style! That’s what <c2>I</c2> call a soldier.” 
<c2>He</c2> now said to <c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1>: 
“Where did <c1>you</c1> attend the cadet school?” 
“<cx>At Prague.</cx>” 
“So <c1>you</c1> attended a cadet school and are not aware that an officer is responsible for his subordinate? That’s 
a nice state of affairs. And then <c1>you</c1> carry on a conversation with <c1>your</c1> <c3>orderly</c3> as if <c3>he</c3> were a close friend of <c1>yours</c1>. <c1>You</c1> allow <c3>him</c3> to talk without being asked. That’s an even nicer state of affairs. In the third place, <c1>you</c1> allow <c3>him</c3> to insult <c1>your</c1> superior officers. And that 
caps all. What is <c1>your</c1> name?” 
“<c1>Lukash</c1>.” 
“And what regiment are you in?” 
“<c1>I</c1> was ” 
“<c2>I</c2>’m not asking where <c1>you</c1> were but where <c1>you</c1> are.” 
“In the 91st regiment, <c2>sir</c2>. They transferred <c1>me</c1> ” 
“ Oh, they transferred <c1>you</c1>, did they? Quite right, too. It won’t do <c1>you</c1> any harm to get to the front as soon as possible with the 91st regiment.” 
“That’s already settled, <c2>sir</c2>.” 
The <c2>major-general</c2> <t2>now</t2> held a lecture about how, of recent years, <c2>he</c2> had observed that <cg>officers</cg> talk to their <cg>subordinates</cg> in a familiar manner, and this <c2>he</c2> held to be a dangerous tendency, inasmuch as it promoted the spread of democratic principles. The <cx>private soldier</cx> must keep 
<cx>himself</cx> to <cx>himself</cx>, <cx>he</cx> must tremble before <cx>his</cx> <cx>superior officer</cx>, <cx>he</cx> must fear <cx>him</cx>. <cg>Officers</cg> must keep the rank-and-file at a distance of ten paces from <cg>them</cg> and not 
allow <cg>them</cg> to think independently or, indeed, to think at all. There was a time when <cg>officers</cg> put the fear of God into the rank-and-file, but nowadays 
The <c2>major-general</c2> made a hopeless gesture with his hand. 
“Nowadays the majority of <cg>officers</cg> absolutely coddle the rank-and-file. That’s all <c2>I</c2> wanted to say.” 
The <c2>major-general</c2> picked up <c2>his</c2> newspaper again and engrossed <c2>himself</c2> in it. <c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1>, as white as a sheet, went out into <p3>the corridor</p3> to settle accounts with <c3>Schweik</c3>. 
<c1>He</c1> found <c3>him</c3> <p4>by the window</p4>, looking as blissful and contented as a baby a month old who has drunk its fill and is now dropping off to sleep. 
The <c1>lieutenant</c1> stopped, beckoned to <c3>Schweik</c3> and pointed to an <p5>empty compartment</p5>. He entered at <c3>Schweik’s</c3> heels and closed the door. “<c3>Schweik</c3>,” <c1>he</c1> said solemnly, “<t2>the time has now come</t2>
for <c3>you</c3> to get the biggest hiffing on record. What on earth did <c3>you</c3> interfere with that <c2>bald-headed gentleman</c2> for? Do you know that <c2>he’s</c2> <c2>Major-General von Schwarzburg</c2>?” 
“Beg to report, <c1>sir</c1>,” announced <c3>Schweik</c3>, with the air of a martyr, “never in <c1>my</c1> life have <c1> </c1> had the least intention of insulting anyone and it’s news to <c3>me</c3> about <c2>him</c2> being <c2>a major-genera </c2>. As true as <c3>I</c3> stand here, <c2>he’s</c2> the living image of <c5>Mr. Purkrdbek</c5>, <c5>agent of the Slavia  Bank</c5>. <c5>He</c5> used to come to <px>our pub</px> and <t1>once</t1>, when <c5>he</c5> fell asleep at <px>a table</px>, some <cx>joker</cx> wrote on <c5>his</c5> head with a copying-ink pencil: ‘Please note our scheme for safeguarding your children’s future as per schedule IIIc enclosed.” 
After a short pause, <c3>Schweik</c3> continued : 
“There was no need for that <c2>gentleman</c2> to get into such a wax over a little mistake like that. It’s an absolute fact <c2>he’s</c2> supposed to have 60,000 to 70,000 hairs, like the average man has, just as the article said. It never struck <c3>me</c3> there was such a thing as <c2>a bald-headed major- general</c2>. Well, that’s what they call a tragic mistake, the same as anybody might make when he passes a remark and somebody else takes it in a wrong way without giving him a chance to explain. I used to know <cx>a tailor</cx> who ” 
<c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1> gave one more look at <c3>Schweik</c3> and then left <p5>the compartment</p5>. <c1>He</c1> returned to his <p6>former seat</p6>, and <t3>after a few minutes</t3> <c3>Schweik</c3>’s guileless countenance appeared in <p7>the doorway</p7> : 
“Beg to report, <c1>sir</c1>, we’ll be <p8>at Tabor</p8> <t4>in five minutes</t4>. The train stops there for <t4>five minutes</t4>. Wouldn’t <c1>you</c1> care to order a little snack of something? Years and years ago they used to have very good ” 
The <c1>lieutenant</c1> jumped up furiously and in <p3>the corridor</p3> <c1>he</c1> said to <c3>Schweik</c3>: 
“ Let me tell <c3>you</c3> once more that the less <c1>I</c1> see of <c3>you</c3>, the better <c1>I</c1> shall like it. If <c1>I</c1> had my way <c1>I’d</c1> never set eyes on <c3>you</c3> again, and <c3>you</c3> can take it from <c1>me</c1> that <c1>I</c1> won’t if <c1>I</c1> can damn well help it. Don’t let <c1>me</c1> see anything of <c3>you</c3>. Keep out of <c1>my</c1> sight, <c1>you</c1> <c1>blithering jackass</c1>, <c1>you</c1>.” 
“Very good, <c1>sir</c1>.” 
<c3>Schweik</c3> saluted, turned smartly to the right-about, in the military manner, and then went to <p3>the end of the  corridor</p3>, where <c3>he</c3> sat down <p9>in a corner</p9> on <p10>the guard’s seat</p10> and entered into a conversation with <c6>a railwayman</c6>. 
“There’s a question <c3>I’d</c3> like to ask <c3>you</c3>, <c6>boss</c6>.” 
<c6>The railwaynnan</c6>, <c6>who</c6> evidently was in no mood for conversation, nodded listlessly, 
“<c3>I</c3> used to know <c7>a chap named Hofmann</c7>,” began <c3>Schweik</c3>, “and <c7>he</c7> always made out that these alarm signals never act, what <c3>I</c3> mean to say, that nothing would happen if you pulled this handle. To tell <c3>you</c3> the honest truth, <c3>I</c3> never gave the matter another thought, but as soon as <c3>I</c3> spotted this alarm outfit here, <c3>I</c3> thought <c3>I’d</c3> like to know what’s what, in case <c3>I</c3> should ever need it.” 
<c3>Schweik</c3> stood up and accompanied <c6>the railwayman</c6> <p11>to the alarm brake</p11> marked: “In case of danger.” <c6>The railwayman</c6> considered it his duty to explain to <c3>Schweik</c3> exactly what the alarm mechanism consisted of. 
“<c7>He</c7> was right when <c7>he</c7> said you’ve got to pull this here handle, but <c7>he</c7> was kidding <c3>you</c3> when <c7>he</c7> made out it don’t act. The tram always stops, because this is connected with all the carriages and the engine. The alarm brake is bound to act.” 
While <c6>he</c6> was saying this, <cg>they</cg> both had <cg>their</cg> hands on the handle of the lever and then — how it happened must remain a mystery — <cg>they</cg> pulled it and the train stopped. 
<cg>They</cg> were quite unable to agree as to who had actually done it and made the alarm signal work. 
<c3>Schweik</c3> declared that <c3>he</c3> couldn’t have done it. 
“It’s a fair marvel to <c3>me</c3>,” he said good-humouredly to <c8>the guard</c8>, “why the train stopped so sudden. It was going, then all at once it stopped. <c3>I’m</c3> more upset about it than what you are.” <c9>A solemn gentleman</c9> took the <c8>guard’s</c8> part and said <c9>he’d</c9> heard <c3>the soldier</c3> start a conversation about alarm signals. 
On the other hand, <c3>Schweik</c3> kept harping upon <c3>his</c3> good name and insisted that it was no advantage to <c3>him</c3> for the train to be late, because <c3>he</c3> was on his way to <p12>the front</p12>. 
“The <c10>station master’ll</c10> tell <c3>you</c3> all about it,” declared <c8>the guard</c8>. “This’ll cost <c3>you</c3> twenty crowns.” 
Meanwhile <cg>the passengers</cg> could be seen climbing down from <p13>the carriages</p13>, <c8>the head guard</c8> blew a whistle, and <cx>a lady</cx> in a panic started running with a portmanteau across <px>the railway track</px> into <px>the fields</px>. 
“ It’s well worth twenty crowns, that it is,” said <c3>Schweik</c3> stolidly, maintaining complete composure. “It’s cheap at the price.” 
<t5>Just then</t5> <c8>the head guard</c8> joined the <cg>audience</cg>. 
“Well, it’s about time <cg>we</cg> made a move,” said <c3>Schweik</c3>. 
“It’s a nuisance when a train’s late. If it was in peace time it wouldn’t matter so much, but now that there’s a war on, all the trains are carrying <cg>troops</cg>, <cg>major-generals</cg>, <cg>lieutenants</cg>, <cg>orderlies</cg>. It’s a risky business being late like that. <cx>Napoleon</cx> was five minutes late at Waterloo and, <cx>emperor</cx> or <cx>no emperor</cx>, <cx>he</cx> got himself into a mess just the same.” 
<t6>At this moment</t6> <c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1> pushed <c1>his</c1> way through the group. <c1>He</c1> was ghastly pale and all <c1>he</c1> could utter was "the word “<c3>Schweik</c3>!” 
<c3>Schweik</c3> saluted and explained : 
“Beg to report, <c1>sir</c1>, <cg>they’re</cg> making out <c1>I</c1> stopped the train. The railway company have got very funny plugs on their emergency brakes. It’s better to keep away from them or else something’ll go wrong and <cg>they’ll</cg> ask you to fork out twenty crowns, the same as they’re asking <c1>me</c1>.” 
<c8>The head guard</c8> had already blown <c8>his</c8> whistle and the train was starting again. <cg>The passengers</cg> returned to <cg>their</cg> seats, and <c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1>, without another word, also went back to <c1>his</c1> compartment. <c8>The guard</c8> now called upon <c3>Schweik</c3> to pay a fine of twenty crowns, as otherwise <c8>he</c8> would have to take him before the <c10>station master</c10> <p8>at Tabor</p8>. 
“That’s all right,” said <c3>Schweik</c3>.
“<c3>I</c3> like talking to educated people. It’ll be a fair treat for <c3>me</c3> to see that <c10>station master</c10> at <p8>Tabor</p8>.” 
When the train arrived <p8>at Tabor</p8>, <c3>Schweik</c3> with all due ceremony went to <c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1> and said : 
“Beg to report, <c1>sir</c1>, <c3>I’m</c3> being taken before <c10>the station master</c10>.” 
<c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1> did not reply. <c1>He</c1> had become completely indifferent to everything. It struck <c1>him</c1> that the best thing he could do was not to care a rap about anybody, whether it was <c3>Schweik</c3> or <c2>the bald-headed major-general</c2>, and to sit quietly where <c1>he</c1> was, to leave the train <p2>at Budejovice</p2>, to report <c1>himself</c1> at <px>the barracks</px> and to proceed to <p12>the front</p12> with a draft. At <p12>the front</p12>, if the worst came to the worst,  <c1>he</c1> would be killed and thus get away from <cx>this appalling world</cx> in which such monstrosities as <c3>Schweik</c3> were knocking about. 
When the train started again.  <c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1> looked <p13>out of the window</p13> and saw <c3>Schweik</c3> standing <p14>on the platform</p14> and engrossed in a solemn colloquy with <c10>the station master</c10>. <c3>Schweik</c3> was surrounded by <cg>a crowd of people</cg> in which several railway uniforms were visible. 
<c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1> heaved a sigh. It was not a sigh of 
pity. <c1>His</c1> heart felt lighter at the thought that <c3>Schweik</c3> 
had been left behind <p14>on the platform</p14>. Even <c2>the bald-headed major-general</c2> did not seem to be quite such <c2>a horrid bugbear</c2>. 
The train had <t7>long since</t7> puffed its way <p2>into Budejovice</p2>, but there was no diminution in <cg>the crowd</cg> round <c3>Schweik</c3>. 
<c3>Schweik</c3> was asserting <c3>his</c3> innocence, and had so convinced <cg>the assembly</cg> that <cx>one lady</cx> remarked : 
“<cg>They’re</cg> bullying <c3>another soldier</c3> again.” 
<cg>The assembly</cg> accepted this view, and <c11>a gentleman</c11> announced to <c10>the station master</c10> that <c11>he</c11> was prepared to pay <c3>Schweik’s</c3> fine for <c3>him</c3>. <c11>He</c11> was convinced that <c3>the soldier</c3> had not done what <c3>he</c3> was accused of. 
Then <cx>a police sergeant</cx> made his appearance and, having grabbed hold of <c12>a man</c12> in the crowd, led <c12>him</c12> away, saying: 
“What d’<c12>you</c12> mean by causing all this disturbance? If that’s the way <c12>you</c12> want <cg>soldiers</cg> treated, how d’<c12>you</c12> expect Austria to win the war?” 
<t8>Meanwhile</t8>, the <c11>worthy person</c11> who believed in <c3>Schweik</c3>’s innocence had paid the fine for <c3>him</c3> and had taken <c3>Schweik</c3> into <p15>the third-class refreshment room</p15>, 
where <c11>he</c11> had treated <c3>him</c3> to beer. And having ascertained that all <c3>his</c3> papers, including <c3>his</c3> railway warrant, were in the possession of <c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1>, <c3>he</c3> generously presented <c3>him</c3> with the sum of five crowns for a ticket and sundry expenses. 
<c3>Schweik</c3> stayed where <c3>he</c3> was, and while <c3>he</c3> was quietly 
drinking <c3>his</c3> way through the five crowns, <cg>the people</cg> <p14>on the platform</p14> who had not witnessed <c3>Schweik’s</c3> interview with <c10>the station master</c10>, and had only seen <cg>a crowd</cg> in the distance, were telling <cg>each other</cg> that <cx>a spy</cx> had been caught taking photographs of <p16>the railway station</p16>, but a <cx>lady</cx> contradicted this rumour by declaring that it wasn’t <cx>a spy</cx> at all, but she had heard that <cx>a dragoon</cx> had struck <cx>an officer</cx> near the ladies’ lavatory because <cx>the officer </cx>was following <cx>his</cx> (<cx>the dragoon’s</cx>) <cx>sweetheart</cx>. These fantastic conjectures were brought to an end by <cg>the police</cg>, who cleared <p14>the platform</p14>. And <c3>Schweik</c3> went on quietly drinking ; <c3>he</c3> wondered with a tender concern what <c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1> had done when <c3>he</c3> reached <p2>Budejovice</p2> and found no signs of <c1>his</c1> <c3>orderly</c3> anywhere. 
<t9>Before the departure</t9> of the slow train, <p15>the third-class refreshment-room</p15> became packed with <cg>travellers</cg>, consisting mostly of <cg>soldiers</cg> belonging to the most varied units and nationalities. The tide of war had swept <cg>them</cg> <px>into hospital</px> and now <cg>they</cg> were again leaving for <p12>the front</p12> to be wounded, mutilated and tortured once more, so as to qualify for a wooden cross on <cg>their</cg> graves. 
“<c3>Ihre</c3> Dokumente, <c3>vasi</c3> tokument," <c13>a sergeant-major</c13> of the military police now remarked to <c3>Schweik</c3> in German and broken Czech. <c13>He</c13> was accompanied by <cg>four soldiers</cg> with fixed bayonets.
“<c3>You</c3> sit, nicht fahren, sit, drink, keep on drink,” <c13>he</c13> continued in his elegant jargon. 
“Haven’t got none, <c13>milacku</c13>,” replied <c3>Schweik</c3>. 
“<c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1> of the 91st regiment took them with <c1>him</c1> and left <c3>me</c3> here in <p16>the station</p16>.” 
“Was ist das Wort: milacek?" asked <c13>the sergeant-major</c13>, turning to <c14>one</c14> of <c13>his</c13> <cg>soldiers</cg>, an <c14>old defence corps man</c14>, <c14>who</c14> replied: 
“Milacek, das ist wie: <c13>Herr Feldwebel</c13>.” 
<c13>The sergeant-major</c13> continued <c13>his</c13> conversation with <c3>Schweik</c3> : 
“Papers, every soldier, without papers, lock up.” 
<cg>They</cg> took <c3>Schweik</c3> accordingly to <p17>the military transport headquarters</p17>. 
“It’s no use, <c3>chum</c3>, <c3>you</c3>’ve got to get it over. So in <c3>you</c3> go,” said the <c14>corporal</c14> to <c3>Schweik</c3> in a sympathetic tone. 
And <c14>he</c14> led <c3>Schweik</c3> into <p18>an office</p18> where, <p19>behind a table</p19> littered with papers, sat a <c15>small lieutenant</c15> <c15>who</c15> looked exceedingly fierce. When <c15>he</c15> saw <c3>Schweik</c3> with the 
<c14>corporal</c14>, <c15>he</c15> remarked: “Aha!” in a significant manner. 
Whereupon <c14>the corporal</c14> explained : 
“Beg to report, <c15>sir</c15>, <c3>this man</c3> was found in <p16>the station</p16> without any papers.” 
<c15>The lieutenant</c15> nodded as if to indicate that <t10>years and years ago</t10> <c15>he</c15> had guessed that precisely on that day and at that hour <c3>Schweik</c3> would be found <p16>in the station</p16> without papers, for anyone looking at <c3>Schweik</c3> <t10>at that moment</t10> could not help feeling convinced that it was quite impossible for <c3>a man of such appearance and bearing</c3> to have any papers on <c3>him</c3>. 
At last <c15>he</c15> asked; 
“What were <c3>you</c3> doing in <p16>the station</p16>?” 
“Beg to report, <c15>sir</c15>, <c3>I</c3> was waiting for the train to <p2>Budejovice</p2>, because <c3>I</c3> want to get to my regiment where <c3>I</c3>’m orderly to <c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1>, but <c3>I</c3> got left behind 
on account of being taken to <c10>the station master</c10> to pay a fine through being suspected of stopping the express <cg>we</cg> were travelling in, by pulling the alarm signal.” 
“Here, <c15>I</c15> can’t make head or tail of this,” shouted <c15>the lieutenant</c15>. “Can’t <c3>you</c3> say what <c3>you</c3>’ve got to say in a straightforward manner, without drivelling away like a lunatic?” 
“Beg to report, <c15>sir</c15>, that <t11>from the very first minute</t11> <c3>I</c3> sat down with <c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1> in <p1>that train</p1> that was to take us to our 91st imperial royal infantry regiment without any hanging about <cg>we</cg> had nothing but bad luck. <t12>First of all</t12> <cg>we</cg> lost a trunk, <t13>then</t13> by way of a change, there was <c2>major-general</c2>, <c2>a bald-headed cove</c2>” 
“Oh, good Lord!” sighed <c15>the lieutenant</c15>. 
And while <c15>the lieutenant</c15> fumed, <c3>Schweik</c3> continued: 
“Well, somehow or other this <c2>bald-headed majorgeneral</c2> got <c2>his</c2> knife into <c3>me</c3> at the very start, and <c1>Lieutenant Lukash</c1>, that’s <c1>the officer</c1> <c3>I</c3>’m orderly to, he sent <c3>me</c3> out 
into <p3>the corridor</p3>. <t13>Then</t13> in the corridor <c3>I</c3> got accused of doing what <c3>I</c3>’ve told <c15>you</c15>. And while <cg>they</cg> were looking into it, <c3>I</c3> got left behind <p14>on the platform</p14>. The train was gone, <c1>the lieutenant</c1> with <c1>his</c1> trunks and <c1>his</c1> papers and with <c3>my</c3> papers was gone too, and there <c3>I</c3> was left in the lurch like an orphan, with no papers and no nothing.” 
<c3>Schweik</c3> gazed at <c15>the lieutenant</c15> with such a touching air of gentleness that <c15>the latter</c15> was quite convinced of the absolute truth of what <c15>he</c15> was hearing from the lips of <c3>this fellow</c3> <c3>who</c3>, to all appearances, was a congenital idiot. <c15>He</c15> now enumerated to <c3>Schweik</c3> all the trains 
which had left for <p2>Budejovice</p2> since the departure of the express, and <c15>he</c15> asked <c3>him</c3> why <c3>he</c3> had missed them as well.
“Beg to report, <c15>sir</c15>,” replied <c3>Schweik</c3>, with a good-humoured smile, “that while <c3>I</c3> was waiting for the next train, <c3>I</c3> got into more trouble through having a few drinks.” 
“<c15>I</c15>’ve never seen such <c3>a fool</c3>,” pondered <c15>the lieutenant</c15>. 
“<c3>He</c3> owns up to everything. <c15>I</c15>’ve had plenty of <cg>them</cg> here, and <cg>they all</cg> swear blind they’ve never done anything. But <c3>this chap</c3> comes up as cool as a cucumber and says: <c3>I</c3> lost all the trains through having a few drinks.” 
<c15>The lieutenant</c15> decided that <t14>the time had now come</t14> to settle the matter once and for all. <c15>He</c15> therefore said in emphatic tones; 
“Now then, <c3>you</c3> <c3>blithering idiot</c3>, <c3>you</c3> <c3>fat-headed lout</c3>, 
go to <p20>the booking-offlce</p20>, buy a ticket and clear off <p2>to Budejovice</p2>. If <c15>I</c15> see any more of <c3>you</c3>, <c15>I</c15>’ll treat <c3>you</c3> as a deserter. Dismiss! ” 
As <c3>Schweik</c3> did not move, but kept <c3>his</c3> hand at the salute at the peak of <c3>his</c3> cap, <c15>the lieutenant</c15> bellowed : 
“Quick march outside, didn’t <c3>you</c3> hear what <c15>I</c15> said? 
<c14>Corporal Paldnek</c14>, take this <c3>drivelling idiot</c3> to <p20>the booking-office</p20> and buy <c3>him</c3> a ticket <p2>to Budejovice</p2>.” 
<t15>After a short interval</t15> <c14>Corporal Paldnek</c14> again appeared at <c15>the lieutenant</c15>’s office. Behind <c14>Paldnek</c14>, through <p20>the open door</p20>, peeped <c3>Schweik’s</c3> good-humoured countenance. 
“What is it now?” 
“Beg to report, <c15>sir</c15>,” whispered <c14>Corporal Palanek</c14> mysteriously, “<c3>he’s</c3> got no money for a ticket and <c14>I’ve</c14> got none, either. <cg>They</cg> won’t let <c3>him</c3> ride free because <c3>he’s</c3> got no papers to show <c3>he’s</c3> going to the regiment.” 
<c15>The lieutenant</c15> promptly delivered a judgment of Solomon to settle the quandary. 
“Then let <c3>him</c3> walk there,” <c15>he</c15> decided, “and when <c3>he</c3> 
gets there <cg>they</cg> can shove him <p21>in clink</p21> for being late. <cg>We</cg> can’t be bothered with <c3>him</c3> <p18>here</p18>.” 
“It’s no use, <c3>chum</c3>,” said <c14>Corporal Paldnek</c14> to <c3>Schweik</c3> when <cg>they</cg> were <p22>outside the office again</p22>, “<c3>you’ll</c3> have to walk <p2>to Budejovice</p2>, <c3>old sport</c3>. <cg>We’ve</cg> got some bread rations in <p23>the guard room</p23>. I’ll give you some to take with you.” 
And <t16>half an hour later</t16>, when they had treated <c3>Schweik</c3> to black coffee, and besides the bread rations had given <c3>him</c3> a packet of army tobacco to take with <c3>him</c3> to the regiment, <c3>he</c3> left <p8>Tabor</p8> at dead of night, singing an old army song. And heaven knows how it happened that 
the <c3>good soldier</c3> <c3>Schweik</c3> instead of turning southward 
towards <p2>Budejovice</p2>, went due west. <c3>He</c3> trudged through snow, wrapped up in <c3>his</c3> army greatcoat, like the last of <cg>Napoleon’s guards</cg> returning from the march on Moscow. 
When <c3>he</c3> got tired of singing, <c3>Schweik</c3> sat down on <p24>a pile of gravel</p24>, lit his pipe and <t17>after having a rest</t17>, trudged on towards new adventures.